[Music]
I'm now going to make a simple hand tied
Bunch um one a lot of these bunches
feature in our new book simple flower
arranging I'm not going to actually
replicate one of those arrangements I'm
going to do something slightly different
and something that might be nice for you
to try at home um to give your mother
for Mother's Day for instance or it
could be a pretty little wedding Bunch
so um I've got my flowers laid out here
roses spray roses hypericum and arantia
nice selection of flowers and Mark's
just conditioning some alcha for me it's
this beautiful fine lime green foliage
which will just sort of bring the whole
thing to life so I'm going to start I'm
going to take some of the smaller
flowers off the
spray and always remember at home don't
throw these away because you can just
collect all these together and make
yourself a little bedside Posey or
something so just don't throw things
away it's always good to keep things and
actually easier to cut them so I'm just
cutting a few of these off so we just
got that lovely top
there and the
arantia do some of those trim that
yes half like that so you got two bits
you can do a few like that yes as Mark's
just done you can actually divide the
stem have a look at the stem first
divide it and then we've got two pieces
rather than just stripping off that
little lower one you've wasted that that
we've got that so we'll do some with
some without yeah cuz I need some tall
some short I'm going to actually take
one tall
piece and just now before you start you
need to think about the binding point
this is The Binding point is where we
hold the bunch to make it the higher The
Binding point the Tighter and smaller
the arrangement is going to be the lower
The Binding point I'm going to get a
much bigger Bunch so I've just got those
three flowers together there and then
I'm going to put one of the bigger
flowers in which is the rose of course
it's lovely rose just going to pop it in
there and you'll notice already where
I'm holding you're beginning to see
angles it's no good just grabbing the
bunch and putting the stem straight up
and down you need to angle every stem so
we're going to get this lovely Dom shape
so you can see that the spir is really
starting to show now so there we go and
the other thing is below the binding
point neverend any foliage that's leaves
because they will poison the water so
make sure yes they rot in the water and
they'll un poison the water so just make
sure that these are completely clean you
can trim them afterwards but just keep
an eye on it as you can see we're
building up a lovely pattern
there quite nice if if you're new to
flower ranging to have a mirror in front
of you the mirrors are there so that you
can hold the bunch ahead of you and look
into the mirror and you get a real
perspective and proper view of how the
the flowers are balancing out cu
obviously your hands aren't quite long
enough to sort of get a proper view
that's as far as you can see whereas if
you hold it like this and you're looking
in a mirror you get that lovely distance
so I've actually got them in my hand now
rather than just with two fingers
because it's obviously getting quite
heavy and I don't want to drop it but
it's quite hard isn't it sort of you get
used to it getting that I'm not gripping
them I've just got I can feel them
sitting in my hand sort of give them all
a quick trim like this so I'm going to
start putting some of this lovely
alchemilla in mark
prepared beautifully prepared
beautifully so there we are just put a
pop a bit of that around like the
berries so if things fall down because
invariably heavy things will drop down
because I'm not gripping the bunch you
just need to carefully fingers either
side of the Rose remember we're not and
just pull them up again remember that
this is the most expensive flower in the
bunch so you want the Roses to sort of
sing you don't want them recessed down
in the bunch you want them brought up
showing like so so I'm going to put a
few more of those
in and as you see the other thing is I'm
actually turning the bunch as I'm going
so you don't need to add like this you
actually can turn it and add do you need
to tie the bouquet off with something we
just use plain old Garden string
gorgeous so string
again where you're you've been holding
your binding point so you need to get as
close to that binding Point as possible
so without without tying your hand to
the
bunch round a couple of times and
strings
good because it sort of holds itself it
doesn't slip whereas Rafia can slip turn
it sideways so I'm going to just turn it
yeah that's better is it so there we go
a simple knot nothing fancy at
all there snip that
off and then we need to trim
it all the same length a pretty little
okay to send to your mother on Mother's
Day or as I say a lovely Bridal Bunch
even a bridesmaid maybe if the bride had
a sort of mass of these roses this would
be pretty for the bride to made tie with
a little pink ribbon so you enjoy having
a go
[Music]